{
    "response_code": 0,
    "results": [
        {
            "difficulty": "1",
            "question": "ས་སྟོང་བསུབ། “དུས་ནི་མི་འགྱུར་་་་་་་་་་་་་་་་་རྣམས་འགྱུར།།”",
            "correct_answer": "མི།",
            "incorrect_answers": [
                "ང་བཅས།",
                "ཀུན་མཉམ།",
                "ཕྱག་མཉམ།"
            ]
        },
        {
            "difficulty": "1",
            "question": "ས་སྟོང་བསུབ། “་་་་་་་་་་་་་་ནི་མི་འགྱུར་མི་རྣམས་འགྱུར།།”",
            "correct_answer": "དུས།",
            "incorrect_answers": [
                "དུག།",
                "ས།",
                "གནས།"
            ]
        },
        {
            "difficulty": "1",
            "question": "“དུས་ནི་མི་འགྱུར་མི་རྣམས་འགྱུར།།” ཟེར་མི་འདི་ ཨིང་སྐད་ནང་ལས་འབད་བ་ཅིན་",
            "correct_answer": "It’s not the times that change but the people who change.",
            "incorrect_answers": [
                "It's not the people who change but the time that changes.",
                "It’s both the time and the people that change.",
                "It’s neither time nor people that change."
            ]
        },
        {
            "difficulty": "1",
            "question": "ས་སྟོང་བསུབ། “དུས་ནི་མི་འགྱུར་མི་རྣམས་་་་་་་་་་་་་།།”",
            "correct_answer": "འགྱུར།",
            "incorrect_answers": [
                "གྱུར།",
                "བྱུར།",
                "འབྱུར།"
            ]
        },
        {
            "difficulty": "1",
            "question": "“དུས་ནི་མི་འགྱུར་མི་རྣམས་འགྱུར།།” ནང་ “དུས”  ཟེར་མི་འདི་ཨིང་སྐད་ལས་འབད་བ་ཅིན",
            "correct_answer": "Time",
            "incorrect_answers": [
                "Person",
                "Place",
                "Location"
            ]
        },
        {
            "difficulty": "1",
            "question": "ས་སྟོང་བསུབ། “་་་་་་་་་་་མེད་པའི་འགན་མ་འབག། ཆུ་མེད་པའི་ཟམ་མ་རྐྱབ།།”",
            "correct_answer": "ཁག་",
            "incorrect_answers": [
                "ཁ་",
                "མཁའ་",
                "ཁཱག་"
            ]
        },
        {
            "difficulty": "1",
            "question": "ས་སྟོང་བསུབ། “ཁག་མེད་པའི་་་་་་་་་་མ་འབག། ཆུ་མེད་པའི་ཟམ་མ་རྐྱབ།།”",
            "correct_answer": "འགན་",
            "incorrect_answers": [
                "གན་",
                "བགན་",
                "གཱན་"
            ]
        },
        {
            "difficulty": "1",
            "question": "ས་སྟོང་བསུབ། “ཁག་མེད་པའི་འགན་མ་་་་་་་་་་། ཆུ་མེད་པའི་ཟམ་མ་རྐྱབ།།”",
            "correct_answer": "འབག་",
            "incorrect_answers": [
                "བ་",
                "བག་",
                "བགས་"
            ]
        },
        {
            "difficulty": "1",
            "question": "ས་སྟོང་བསུབ། “ཁག་མེད་པའི་འགན་མ་འབག་། ་་་་་་་་་་་མེད་པའི་ཟམ་མ་རྐྱབ།།”",
            "correct_answer": "ཆུ་",
            "incorrect_answers": [
                "འཁྱུ་",
                "ཕྱུ་",
                "འཆུ་"
            ]
        },
        {
            "difficulty": "1",
            "question": "ས་སྟོང་བསུབ། “ཁག་མེད་པའི་འགན་མ་འབག་། ཆུ་མེད་པའི་་་་་་་་་་མ་རྐྱབ།།”",
            "correct_answer": "ཟམ་",
            "incorrect_answers": [
                "འཛམ་",
                "ཛམ་",
                "བཛཱམ་"
            ]
        },
        {
            "difficulty": "1",
            "question": "ས་སྟོང་བསུབ། “་་་་་་་་་་་་་་ཀྱིས་མནོ་ཚད་མ་འབད།། ཁ་ལས་འཐོན་ཚད་མ་སླབ།།”",
            "correct_answer": "སེམས་",
            "incorrect_answers": [
                "སེམ་",
                "བསེམ་",
                "གསེམ་"
            ]
        },
        {
            "difficulty": "1",
            "question": "ས་སྟོང་བསུབ། “སེམས་ཀྱིས་་་་་་་་་་་་་་་མ་འབད།། ཁ་ལས་འཐོན་ཚད་མ་སླབ།།”",
            "correct_answer": "མནོ་ཚད་",
            "incorrect_answers": [
                "ཤེས་ཚད་",
                "མཐོང་ཚད་",
                "ག་མནོཝ་"
            ]
        },
        {
            "difficulty": "1",
            "question": "ས་སྟོང་བསུབ། “སེམས་ཀྱིས་མནོ་ཚད་མ་་་་་་་་་་་་།། ཁ་ལས་འཐོན་ཚད་མ་སླབ།།”",
            "correct_answer": "འབད",
            "incorrect_answers": [
                "སྦེ",
                "འབདན",
                "བེད་"
            ]
        },
        {
            "difficulty": "1",
            "question": "ས་སྟོང་བསུབ། “སེམས་ཀྱིས་མནོ་ཚད་མ་འབད།། ་་་་་་་་་་་་་་་འཐོན་ཚད་མ་སླབ།།”",
            "correct_answer": "ཁ་ལས་",
            "incorrect_answers": [
                "ཁ་ནང་",
                "ཁཱ་ནང་",
                "ཁཱ་ལས་"
            ]
        },
        {
            "difficulty": "1",
            "question": "ས་སྟོང་བསུབ། “སེམས་ཀྱིས་མནོ་ཚད་མ་འབད།། ཁ་ལས་འཐོན་ཚད་་་་་་་་་་་་་།།”",
            "correct_answer": "མ་སླབ",
            "incorrect_answers": [
                "སླབ་དགོ",
                "སླབ་བཏུབ",
                "སླབ་མི་བཏུབ"
            ]
        },
        {
            "difficulty": "1",
            "question": "ས་སྟོང་བསུབ། “བསམ་པ་་་་་་་་་་་་་ན་ས་དང་ལམ་ཡང་་་་་་་་་་་་།། བསམ་པ་ངན་ན་ས་དང་ལམ་ཡང་ངན།།”",
            "correct_answer": "བཟང་",
            "incorrect_answers": [
                "ལེགས་",
                "ཕན་",
                "འཟང་"
            ]
        },
        {
            "difficulty": "1",
            "question": "ས་སྟོང་བསུབ། “བསམ་པ་བཟང་ན་ས་དང་་་་་་་་་་་་ཡང་བཟང་།། བསམ་པ་ངན་ན་ས་དང་་་་་་་་་་་ཡང་ངན།།”",
            "correct_answer": "ལམ་",
            "incorrect_answers": [
                "གནམ་",
                "ནམས་",
                "ལཱམ་"
            ]
        },
        {
            "difficulty": "1",
            "question": "ས་སྟོང་བསུབ། “་་་་་་་་་་་་་་བཟང་ན་ས་དང་ལམ་ཡང་བཟང་།། ་་་་་་་་་་་་་་་ངན་ན་ས་དང་ལམ་ཡང་ངན།།”",
            "correct_answer": "བསམ་པ་",
            "incorrect_answers": [
                "འསམ་པ་",
                "སམས་པ་",
                "འཙམ་པ་"
            ]
        },
        {
            "difficulty": "1",
            "question": "ས་སྟོང་བསུབ། “བསམ་པ་བཟང་ན་ས་དང་ལམ་ཡང་བཟང་།། བསམ་པ་་་་་་་་་་་་ན་ས་དང་ལམ་ཡང་་་་་་་་་་་་་།།”",
            "correct_answer": "ངན་",
            "incorrect_answers": [
                "ཉན་",
                "འངན་",
                "ངནན་"
            ]
        },
        {
            "difficulty": "1",
            "question": "“བསམ་པ་བཟང་ན་ས་དང་ལམ་ཡང་བཟང་།། བསམ་པ་ངན་ན་ས་དང་ལམ་ཡང་ངན།།” ཟེར་མི་འདི་ ཨིང་སྐད་ནང་ལས་འབད་བ་ཅིན་",
            "correct_answer": "If the intentions are good, Even the land and the path are good; If the intentions are evil, Even the land and the path are evil.",
            "incorrect_answers": [
                "If the character is good, even the appearance doesn’t matter; If the character is worse, even the beauty gets hidden. ",
                "If the works are good, even the product is good; if the works are bad, even the result will be bad. ",
                "If the speech is good, even an enemy can be trapped; if the speech is harsh, even the closest won’t listen. "
            ]
        },
        {
            "difficulty": "1",
            "question": "ས་སྟོང་བསུབ། “་་་་་་་་་་་་་་ལུ་མ་བརྩི།། དོན་ལུ་བརྩི།།”",
            "correct_answer": "ཞག་",
            "incorrect_answers": [
                "གཞག་",
                "བཞག་",
                "ཞགས་"
            ]
        },
        {
            "difficulty": "1",
            "question": "ས་སྟོང་བསུབ། “ཞག་ལུ་་་་་་་་་་་་་།། དོན་ལུ་བརྩི།།”",
            "correct_answer": "མ་བརྩི",
            "incorrect_answers": [
                "བརྩི་དགོ",
                "བརྩི་ནི་མི་འོང",
                "བརྩི་འབད"
            ]
        },
        {
            "difficulty": "1",
            "question": "ས་སྟོང་བསུབ། “ཞག་ལུ་མ་བརྩི།། ་་་་་་་་་་་་་་་ལུ་བརྩི།།”",
            "correct_answer": "དོན་",
            "incorrect_answers": [
                "གདན་",
                "དན་",
                "བདན་"
            ]
        },
        {
            "difficulty": "1",
            "question": "ས་སྟོང་བསུབ། “ཞག་ལུ་མ་བརྩི།། དོན་ལུ་་་་་་་་་་་།།”",
            "correct_answer": "བརྩི",
            "incorrect_answers": [
                "མ་བརྩི",
                "བརྩི་དགོ",
                "བརྩི་ད"
            ]
        },
        {
            "difficulty": "1",
            "question": "“ཞག་ལུ་མ་བརྩི།། དོན་ལུ་བརྩི།།” ཟེར་མི་འདི་ ཨིང་སྐད་ནང་ལས་འབད་བ་ཅིན་",
            "correct_answer": "Do not consider the number of days, consider the purpose.",
            "incorrect_answers": [
                "Do not count the number of days, but the number of nights.",
                "Do not count the number of lights, but consider its illumination power. ",
                "Do not consider the number of nights, but consider its darkness. "
            ]
        },
        {
            "difficulty": "1",
            "question": "ས་སྟོང་བསུབ། “་་་་་་་་་་་་ཞིམ་རོགས་ལུ་བྱིན།། ལུས་དལཝ་རང་སྡོད།།”",
            "correct_answer": "ཟས་",
            "incorrect_answers": [
                "བཟས་",
                "གཟས་",
                "གཟེས་"
            ]
        },
        {
            "difficulty": "1",
            "question": "ས་སྟོང་བསུབ། “ཟས་ཞིམ་་་་་་་་་་་ལུ་བྱིན།། ལུས་དལཝ་རང་སྡོད།།”",
            "correct_answer": "རོགས་",
            "incorrect_answers": [
                "རོ་",
                "ག་ར་",
                "གེ ར་ "
            ]
        },
        {
            "difficulty": "1",
            "question": "ས་སྟོང་བསུབ། “ཟས་ཞིམ་རོགས་ལུ་་་་་་་་་་་།། ལུས་དལཝ་རང་སྡོད།།”",
            "correct_answer": "བྱིན",
            "incorrect_answers": [
                "སྤྲོད",
                "སྤྲོལ",
                "སྦྱིན"
            ]
        },
        {
            "difficulty": "1",
            "question": "ས་སྟོང་བསུབ། “ཟས་ཞིམ་རོགས་ལུ་བྱིན།། ་་་་་་་་་་དལཝ་རང་སྡོད།།”",
            "correct_answer": "ལུས་",
            "incorrect_answers": [
                "ལུད་",
                "གཟུགས་",
                "སྐུ་གཟུགས་"
            ]
        },
        {
            "difficulty": "1",
            "question": "ས་སྟོང་བསུབ། “ཟས་ཞིམ་རོགས་ལུ་བྱིན།། ལུས་དལཝ་རང་་་་་་་་་་།།”",
            "correct_answer": "སྡོད",
            "incorrect_answers": [
                "བཞག",
                "གཞུགས",
                "གཞག"
            ]
        },
        {
            "difficulty": "1",
            "question": "ས་སྟོང་བསུབ། “་་་་་་་་་་་་་་་ཁ་མ་ཤེས།། རང་ཁ་བྱང་།།”",
            "correct_answer": "རོགས་",
            "incorrect_answers": [
                "གཞན་",
                "རོ་",
                "ཞན་"
            ]
        },
        {
            "difficulty": "1",
            "question": "ས་སྟོང་བསུབ། “རོགས་ཁ་་་་་་་་་་།། རང་ཁ་བྱང་།།”",
            "correct_answer": "མ་ཤེས",
            "incorrect_answers": [
                "མི་ཤེས",
                "མ་ཤེསན",
                "མ་ཤེས་བར"
            ]
        },
        {
            "difficulty": "1",
            "question": "ས་སྟོང་བསུབ། “རོགས་ཁ་མ་ཤེས།། ་་་་་་་་་་་་ཁ་བྱང་།།”",
            "correct_answer": "རང་",
            "incorrect_answers": [
                "ང་བཅས་རའི་",
                "རང་གི་",
                "ང་བཅས་"
            ]
        },
        {
            "difficulty": "1",
            "question": "ས་སྟོང་བསུབ། “རོགས་ཁ་མ་ཤེས།། རང་ཁ་་་་་་་་་་་་།།”",
            "correct_answer": "བྱང",
            "incorrect_answers": [
                "གྱང",
                "གྱངས",
                "བྱངས"
            ]
        },
        {
            "difficulty": "1",
            "question": "“རོགས་ཁ་མ་ཤེས།། རང་ཁ་བྱང་།།” ཟེར་མི་འདི་ ཨིང་སྐད་ནང་ལས་འབད་བ་ཅིན་",
            "correct_answer": "Does not know other people’s language; Has lost one’s own language!",
            "incorrect_answers": [
                "Knowing other people’s language; Helps in conversing with other people!",
                "Not knowing other people’s language; It will affect your communication skill!",
                "Knowing other people’s language; it will affect your own language!"
            ]
        },
        {
            "difficulty": "1",
            "question": "ས་སྟོང་བསུབ། “་་་་་་་་་་་་་་་་་་་གཏད་པའི་མི་གིས་ཧིང་བརྐུ།།”",
            "correct_answer": "བློ་",
            "incorrect_answers": [
                "ལོ་",
                "རློ་",
                "སློ་"
            ]
        },
        {
            "difficulty": "1",
            "question": "ས་སྟོང་བསུབ། “བློ་་་་་་་་་་་་་་་་པའི་མི་གིས་ཧིང་བརྐུ།།”",
            "correct_answer": "གཏད་",
            "incorrect_answers": [
                "སླབ་",
                "གསང་",
                "གཡིབ་"
            ]
        },
        {
            "difficulty": "1",
            "question": "ས་སྟོང་བསུབ། “བློ་གཏད་པའི་མི་གིས་་་་་་་་་་་བརྐུ།།”",
            "correct_answer": "ཧིང་",
            "incorrect_answers": [
                "སྙིང་",
                "སེམས་",
                "དོན་ཧིང་"
            ]
        },
        {
            "difficulty": "1",
            "question": "ས་སྟོང་བསུབ། “བློ་གཏད་པའི་མི་གིས་ཧིང་་་་་་་་་་་།།”",
            "correct_answer": "བརྐུ",
            "incorrect_answers": [
                "རྐུ",
                "དཀྲུགས",
                "བརྐོ"
            ]
        },
        {
            "difficulty": "1",
            "question": "“བློ་གཏད་པའི་མི་གིས་ཧིང་བརྐུ།།” ཟེར་མི་འདི་ ཨིང་སྐད་ནང་ལས་འབད་བ་ཅིན་",
            "correct_answer": "He who is trusted steals one’s heart secrets. ",
            "incorrect_answers": [
                "He who is trusted gives one the happiness. ",
                "He who trusts too much is betrayed.",
                "He who trusts too much is a loyal person. "
            ]
        },
        {
            "difficulty": "1",
            "question": "ས་སྟོང་བསུབ། བུ་་་་་་་་་་་་་་་རུང་ཕ་མའི་བསྐོར་གཏམ་དགོ།",
            "correct_answer": "མཁས་",
            "incorrect_answers": [
                "མན་",
                "ལེགས་",
                "བཟང་"
            ]
        },
        {
            "difficulty": "1",
            "question": "ས་སྟོང་བསུབ། བུ་མཁས་རུང་་་་་་་་་་་་་་་་་་བསྐོར་གཏམ་དགོ།",
            "correct_answer": "ཕ་མའི་",
            "incorrect_answers": [
                "བླ་མའི་",
                "ཆ་རོགས་ཀྱི་",
                "སློབ་དཔོན་གྱི་"
            ]
        },
        {
            "difficulty": "1",
            "question": "ས་སྟོང་བསུབ། བུ་མཁས་རུང་ཕ་མའི་་་་་་་་་་་་་་་་་གཏམ་དགོ།",
            "correct_answer": "བསྐོར་",
            "incorrect_answers": [
                "ཀོར་",
                "བསྐར་",
                "ཀར་"
            ]
        },
        {
            "difficulty": "1",
            "question": "ས་སྟོང་བསུབ། བུ་མཁས་རུང་ཕ་མའི་བསྐོར་་་་་་་་་་་་་་་་་་དགོ།",
            "correct_answer": "གཏམ་",
            "incorrect_answers": [
                "བཏམ་",
                "ཏམ་",
                "དམ་"
            ]
        },
        {
            "difficulty": "1",
            "question": "བུ་མཁས་རུང་ཕ་མའི་བསྐོར་གཏམ་དགོ།  ཟེར་མི་འདི་ ཨིང་སྐད་ནང་ལས་འབད་བ་ཅིན་",
            "correct_answer": "Even if learned, the child will need the parent’s good counsel",
            "incorrect_answers": [
                "Even if learned, the child will not need the parent’s good counsel",
                "Even if learned, the parent will need the child’s good counsel",
                "Even if learned, the child will need the parent’s bad counsel"
            ]
        },
        {
            "difficulty": "1",
            "question": "ས་སྟོང་བསུབ། གྱང་་་་་་་་་་་་་་རོ་བགོ་མ་གྱོན།།",
            "correct_answer": "རུང་",
            "incorrect_answers": [
                "རང་",
                "རིང་",
                "རེང་"
            ]
        },
        {
            "difficulty": "1",
            "question": "“ གྱང་རུང་རོ་བགོ་མ་གྱོན།། ” ནང་ “གྱང”  ཟེར་མི་འདི་ཨིང་སྐད་ལས་འབད་བ་ཅིན",
            "correct_answer": "Feel cold",
            "incorrect_answers": [
                "Feel hot",
                "Feel happy",
                "Feel sad"
            ]
        },
        {
            "difficulty": "1",
            "question": "གྱང་རུང་རོ་བགོ་མ་གྱོན།།  ཟེར་མི་འདི་ ཨིང་སྐད་ནང་ལས་འབད་བ་ཅིན་",
            "correct_answer": "Do not wear the clothes of the dead, however cold.",
            "incorrect_answers": [
                "Wear the clothes of the dead when hot.",
                "Wear the clothes of the dead, however cold.",
                "None"
            ]
        },
        {
            "difficulty": "1",
            "question": "གྱང་རུང་རོ་བགོ་མ་གྱོན།།  ནང་ “བགོ”  ཟེར་མི་འདི་ཨིང་སྐད་ལས་འབད་བ་ཅིན",
            "correct_answer": "Cloth",
            "incorrect_answers": [
                "Food",
                "Money",
                "Door"
            ]
        },
        {
            "difficulty": "1",
            "question": "གྱང་རུང་རོ་བགོ་མ་གྱོན།།   ནང་ “གྱོན”  ཟེར་མི་འདི་ཨིང་སྐད་ལས་འབད་བ་ཅིན",
            "correct_answer": "To wear",
            "incorrect_answers": [
                "Cucumber",
                "To walk",
                "None"
            ]
        },
        {
            "difficulty": "2",
            "question": "ས་སྟོང་བསུབ “གཅེས་ཕྲུག་དགའ་ཞོར་སྐྱིད་ཞོར་ལ་་་་་་་་་་་་་་་་་་་།།” ",
            "correct_answer": "ཡོན་ཏན་ཤེས་པ་མི་འོང",
            "incorrect_answers": [
                "བརྩེ་གདུང་ཆེ་བ་འོང་",
                "ཡོན་ཏན་ཤེས་པ་ཟོང་",
                "1བརྩེ་གདུང་མ་འོང་"
            ]
        },
        {
            "difficulty": "2",
            "question": "“གཅེས་ཕྲུག་དགའ་ཞོར་སྐྱིད་ཞོར་ལ་ཡོན་ཏན་ཤེས་པ་མི་འོང་།།” ཟེར་མི་འདི་ ཨིང་སྐད་ནང་ལས་འབད་བ་ཅིན་ ",
            "correct_answer": "A child who is shown love and affection through an excess of joy and peace will not be able to learn much.",
            "incorrect_answers": [
                "A child who is shown love and affection through an excess of joy and peace will be nurtured well. ",
                "A child who is shown love and affection through an excess of joy and peace will not live an independent life. ",
                "A child who is shown love and affection through an excess of joy and peace will not be a good leader. "
            ]
        },
        {
            "difficulty": "2",
            "question": "“གཅེས་ཕྲུག་དགའ་ཞོར་སྐྱིད་ཞོར་ལ་ཡོན་ཏན་ཤེས་པ་མི་འོང་  ནང་ “དགའ་ཞོར་སྐྱིད་ཞོར”  ཟེར་མི་འདི་ཨིང་སྐད་ལས་འབད་བ་ཅིན ",
            "correct_answer": "Joy and peace. ",
            "incorrect_answers": [
                "Laughter and peace.",
                "Love and serenity. ",
                "Laughter and comfort."
            ]
        },
        {
            "difficulty": "2",
            "question": "What is the impact of excessive love and affection on a child's learning? ",
            "correct_answer": "It has a negative impact. ",
            "incorrect_answers": [
                "It has no impact. ",
                "It has a positive impact. ",
                "Does not provide enough information to determine the impact. "
            ]
        },
        {
            "difficulty": "2",
            "question": "What is the importance of the translated proverb “ It's not the times that change but the people who change ” ",
            "correct_answer": "It emphasizes the role of personal responsibility in adapting to changing circumstances. ",
            "incorrect_answers": [
                "It encourages people to change with the times. ",
                "It highlights the inevitability of change. ",
                "It argues that people are more important than times."
            ]
        },
        {
            "difficulty": "2",
            "question": "ས་སྟོང་བསུབ། “ ་་་་་་་་་་་་་་་་་་་་་་་་་་་་་་་་་་་་་།། ཕ་ཞིང་ཨིན་བྱག་ཡང་ཧྲམ།། རོགས་སྐལ་ཨིན་མར་ཡང་མི་བཞུ།།” ",
            "correct_answer": "རང་སྐལ་ཨིན་རྡོ་ཡང་རྨུར ",
            "incorrect_answers": [
                "རང་གི་སྐལཝ་རྡོ་ཨིན་རུང་རྨུར་དགོ ",
                "རང་སྐལ་ལྕགས་ཨིན་ཡང་རྨུར",
                "རང་གི་སྐལཝ་ལྕགས་ཨིན་རུང་རྨུར་དགོ"
            ]
        },
        {
            "difficulty": "2",
            "question": "“ རང་སྐལ་ཨིན་རྡོ་ཡང་རྨུར།། ཕ་ཞིང་ཨིན་བྱག་ཡང་ཧྲམ།། རོགས་སྐལ་ཨིན་མར་ཡང་མི་བཞུ།། ”  ནང་ “ རང་སྐལ་ཨིན་རྡོ་ཡང་རྨུར།། ”  ཟེར་མི་འདི་ཨིང་སྐད་ལས་འབད་བ་ཅིན ",
            "correct_answer": "If it concerns one’s own interest, one can chew even a stone; ",
            "incorrect_answers": [
                "If it concerns one’s own responsibility, one should even chew a metal;",
                "If it concerns one’s own interest, one should even swallow poison;",
                "If it concerns one’s own responsibility, one should even chew betel nuts. "
            ]
        },
        {
            "difficulty": "2",
            "question": "“ ཕ་ཞིང་ཨིན་བྱག་ཡང་ཧྲམ།།” ཟེར་མི་འདི་ ཨིང་སྐད་ནང་ལས་འབད་བ་ཅིན་",
            "correct_answer": "One will do anything to protect their family’s property.  ",
            "incorrect_answers": [
                "One will only act in their family’s if it is easy to do so. ",
                "One will only act in their family’s interest if they are not required to make sacrifices.",
                "One will never do anything that is against their family’s interest."
            ]
        },
        {
            "difficulty": "2",
            "question": "“རོགས་སྐལ་ཨིན་མར་ཡང་མི་བཞུ།།” ཟེར་མི་འདི་ ཨིང་སྐད་ནང་ལས་འབད་བ་ཅིན་",
            "correct_answer": "One will never act in the interest of others. ",
            "incorrect_answers": [
                "One will always act in the interest of others, even if it is difficult. ",
                "One will act in the interest of others only if they stand to benefit as well. ",
                "One will act in the interest of others only if it is easy to do so."
            ]
        },
        {
            "difficulty": "2",
            "question": "According to the translated proverb “ If it concerns one’s own interest, one can chew even a stone; If it concerns ancestral land, one can demolish even a cliff; If it concerns other’s interest, even the butter cannot melt. ”, what action would someone take if it concerns others’ interest?",
            "correct_answer": "They would act in their own self-interest.  ",
            "incorrect_answers": [
                "They would prioritize the interest of others over their own. ",
                "They would seek the advice of others before making a decision.",
                "They would remain natural and take no action. ."
            ]
        },
        {
            "difficulty": "2",
            "question": "ས་སྟོང་བསུབ། “་་་་་་་་་་་་་་་་་་་་་་་ ལྷ་པ་ལས་ཀྱིས་བཏགས་འོང་།། ”",
            "correct_answer": "རུ་ཏོ་ཡོདན་",
            "incorrect_answers": [
                "ར་ཏོ་ཡོདན་",
                "ཁ་ར་ཡོདན་",
                "གདོང་ར་ཡོདན་"
            ]
        },
        {
            "difficulty": "2",
            "question": "“ རུ་ཏོ་ཡོདན་ ལྷ་པ་ལས་ཀྱིས་བཏགས་འོང་།། ” ཟེར་མི་འདི་ ཨིང་སྐད་ནང་ལས་འབད་བ་ཅིན་",
            "correct_answer": "If bone is there, the growth of flesh is natural. ",
            "incorrect_answers": [
                "Growth of muscles is dependent on the presence of bones.",
                "Strong bones lead to growth of healthy flesh.",
                "Bones and flesh have no correlation. "
            ]
        },
        {
            "difficulty": "2",
            "question": "“ རུ་ཏོ་ཡོདན་ ལྷ་པ་ལས་ཀྱིས་བཏགས་འོང་།། ” ནང་ “ རུ་ཏོ ”  ཟེར་མི་འདི་ཨིང་སྐད་ལས་འབད་བ་ཅིན",
            "correct_answer": "Bone",
            "incorrect_answers": [
                "Flesh",
                "Blood",
                "Nerve  "
            ]
        },
        {
            "difficulty": "2",
            "question": "Which of the following is a natural consequence of the presence of bones:",
            "correct_answer": "Growth of flesh",
            "incorrect_answers": [
                "Growth of hair",
                "Growth of nails",
                "None"
            ]
        },
        {
            "difficulty": "2",
            "question": "Which of the following is a common interpretation of the proverb 'Do not perform whatever occurs in mind, Do not pronounce whatever in the mouth'?",
            "correct_answer": "Think before you speak",
            "incorrect_answers": [
                "Always speak your mind",
                "Act on impulse",
                "None"
            ]
        },
        {
            "difficulty": "2",
            "question": "ས་སྟོང་བསུབ། “ སྤྲང་པོའི་བུུ་་་་་་་་་་་་་་་་་་་་་། ཕྱུག་པོའི་བུ་གསོཝ་ཁག། ”",
            "correct_answer": "བཀོལཝ་ཁག",
            "incorrect_answers": [
                "སྐྱོང་བ་ཁག",
                "བཏུལ་བ་ཁག",
                "གསོཝ་ཁག"
            ]
        },
        {
            "difficulty": "2",
            "question": "“ སྤྲང་པོའི་བུུ་བཀོལཝ་ཁག། ཕྱུག་པོའི་བུ་གསོཝ་ཁག། ” ཟེར་མི་འདི་ ཨིང་སྐད་ནང་ལས་འབད་བ་ཅིན་",
            "correct_answer": "Difficult to make a poor person’s son work; Difficult to to rear rich person’s son. ",
            "incorrect_answers": [
                "It is easy to make a poor person’s so work but difficult to rear a rich person’s son. ",
                "It is difficult to make a rich person’s son work but easy to rear a poor person’s son. ",
                "None"
            ]
        },
        {
            "difficulty": "2",
            "question": "What does the proverb imply about the sons of poor people?",
            "correct_answer": "They are difficult to motivate and get working. ",
            "incorrect_answers": [
                "They are lazy and unproductive.",
                "They are born into privilege and have an entitled attitude. ",
                " None"
            ]
        },
        {
            "difficulty": "2",
            "question": "What does the proverb imply about the sons of rich people?",
            "correct_answer": "They are more entitled and privileged than the sons of poor people.",
            "incorrect_answers": [
                "They are inherently lazy and unproductive.",
                "They are difficult to motivate and get working. ",
                " None"
            ]
        },
        {
            "difficulty": "2",
            "question": "What is the importance of the 'land and the path' in the proverb?",
            "correct_answer": "They represent external factors that can influence the outcome of an action.",
            "incorrect_answers": [
                "They represent internal factors that can influence the outcome of an action.",
                "They have no significance in the proverb.",
                " None"
            ]
        },
        {
            "difficulty": "2",
            "question": "་ས་སྟོང་བསུབ། “ ་་་་་་་་་་་་་་་་་་་པར་མར་མི་བཞུ།། ”",
            "correct_answer": "བྱི་ལི་ཁོག",
            "incorrect_answers": [
                "བྱི་ཙི་ཁོག",
                "བྱ་ཡའི་ཁོག",
                " བ་གི་ཁོག "
            ]
        },
        {
            "difficulty": "2",
            "question": "“ བྱི་ལི་ཁོག་པར་མར་མི་བཞུ།། ” ཟེར་མི་འདི་ ཨིང་སྐད་ནང་ལས་འབད་བ་ཅིན་",
            "correct_answer": "Difficult for the cat to digest butter. ",
            "incorrect_answers": [
                "Difficult for the cat to swallow butter. ",
                "Difficult for the cat to eat butter.",
                "Difficult for the cat to taste butter.  "
            ]
        },
        {
            "difficulty": "2",
            "question": "“ བྱི་ལི་ཁོག་པར་མར་མི་བཞུ།། ” ཟེར་མི་དཔྱེ་གཏམ་ནང་ སེམས་ཅན་ག་འདི་ལུ་དཔྱེ་བཞག་ནུག? སེམས་ཅན་འདི་གི་མིང་ ཨིང་སྐད་ལས་འབད་བ་ཅིན་",
            "correct_answer": "Cat.  ",
            "incorrect_answers": [
                "Rat.",
                "Bird.",
                "Cow "
            ]
        },
        {
            "difficulty": "2",
            "question": "འོག་གི་གདམ་ཁ་ཚུ་ནང་ལས་ བྱི་ལི་མར་བཟའཝ་ད་ལཱ་ཁག་རྐྱབ་འོང་ ཟེར་མི་འདི་ངོས་འཛིན་འབད།",
            "correct_answer": "བྱི་ལི་ཁོག་པར་མར་མི་བཞུ།།",
            "incorrect_answers": [
                "ཕག་ཤ་ཟ་ཚད་འཛུམ་སེག་སེ།། ཕག་རིན་འཇལ་ཚད་གནག་ལོག་ལོ།།",
                "ཕྱི་མ་དགཔ་ཆུ་གིས་བཤལ།། ནང་མ་དགཔ་གཏམ་གྱིས་བཤལ།།",
                "རུ་ཏོ་ཡོདན་ ལྷ་པ་ལས་ཀྱིས་བཏགས་འོང་།། "
            ]
        },
        {
            "difficulty": "2",
            "question": "Who is most likely to appreciate the message of the translated proverb “Do not consider the number of days, consider the purpose”?",
            "correct_answer": "Someone who is very busy.",
            "incorrect_answers": [
                "Someone who is retired.",
                "Someone who is young.",
                "Someone who is wealthy. "
            ]
        },
        {
            "difficulty": "2",
            "question": "ས་སྟོང་བསུབ། “ ལ་གཅིག་བརྒལན།། ་་་་་་་་་་་་་་་་་་་་་་་་་་་་་།། ”",
            "correct_answer": "ལུངམ་གཅིག་སྤུབས",
            "incorrect_answers": [
                "ལཱ་ཁག་མེད",
                "རང་སེམས་དགའ",
                "མར་ཁ་འགྱོ"
            ]
        },
        {
            "difficulty": "2",
            "question": "“ ལ་གཅིག་བརྒལན།། ལུངམ་གཅིག་སྤུབས།། ” ཟེར་མི་འདི་ ཨིང་སྐད་ནང་ལས་འབད་བ་ཅིན་",
            "correct_answer": "Cross one mountain pass; And there’s still the dark canopy of a valley to cross. ",
            "incorrect_answers": [
                "Get done one work; And then another difficult task comes. ",
                "Cross one mountain pass; And then you reach a better place.",
                "Get the difficult task done; And then you can easily do the easy one"
            ]
        },
        {
            "difficulty": "2",
            "question": "“ ལ་གཅིག་བརྒལན།། ལུངམ་གཅིག་སྤུབས།། ” ནང་ “ ལ ”  ཟེར་མི་འདི་ཨིང་སྐད་ལས་འབད་བ་ཅིན",
            "correct_answer": "Mountain Pass",
            "incorrect_answers": [
                "Task ",
                "Honorific word",
                "Dzongkha letter"
            ]
        },
        {
            "difficulty": "2",
            "question": "What is the message of the translated proverb “ Cross one mountain pass; And there is still the dark canopy of a valley to cross ”?",
            "correct_answer": "Obstacles are a natural part of the journey. ",
            "incorrect_answers": [
                "The journey is more important than the destination. ",
                "Success is often followed by failure. ",
                "Life is unpredictable. "
            ]
        },
        {
            "difficulty": "2",
            "question": "What message does the translated proverb “ Let good food be given to others; Let freedom and leisure be one's own ” relay?",
            "correct_answer": "It is important to balance one’s own needs with the needs of others. ",
            "incorrect_answers": [
                "It is important to share good things with others.  ",
                "One should always prioritize their own needs over others. ",
                "One should always be generous and selfless. "
            ]
        },
        {
            "difficulty": "2",
            "question": "ས་སྟོང་བསུབ། “ ཆུ་མ་འོངམ་ལས་་་་་་་་་་་་་་་་་་་།། ནད་མ་འོངམ་ལས་རིམ་གྲོ་འབད།། ”",
            "correct_answer": "གཡུར་བ་བསལ",
            "incorrect_answers": [
                "ཟམ་པ་རྐྱབ",
                "གཡུ་བ་བསལ",
                "རྫམ་པ་རྐྱབ"
            ]
        },
        {
            "difficulty": "2",
            "question": " ཆུ་མ་འོངམ་ལས་གཡུར་བ་བསལ།། ” ཟེར་མི་འདི་ ཨིང་སྐད་ནང་ལས་འབད་བ་ཅིན་",
            "correct_answer": "Clean up the drains before water arrives. ",
            "incorrect_answers": [
                "Clean up the turquoise with the clean water.",
                "Clean up the blocked drainage with the water. ",
                "Clean up the turquoise before it gets washed away by water."
            ]
        },
        {
            "difficulty": "2",
            "question": " 'ནད་མ་འོངམ་ལས་རིམ་གྲོ་འབད།།' ཟེར་མི་འདི་ ཨིང་སྐད་ནང་ལས་འབད་བ་ཅིན་",
            "correct_answer": "Carry Out the rituals before the disease arrives. ",
            "incorrect_answers": [
                "Carry Out the rituals only when a person is sick.",
                "The patient must perform a ritual by themselves.",
                "Never carry out the rituals. "
            ]
        },
        {
            "difficulty": "2",
            "question": "What message do the translated proverb 'Clean up the drains before water arrives; Carry out the rituals before disease arrives' relay?",
            "correct_answer": "Be proactive and take action before a problem occurs.",
            "incorrect_answers": [
                "Don't worry about it until it becomes a problem.",
                " Let someone else deal with it.",
                "It's too late to do anything once the problem has started."
            ]
        },
        {
            "difficulty": "2",
            "question": "Which of the following best describes the significance of the translated proverb 'Does not know other people's language; Has lost one's own language'?",
            "correct_answer": "The proverb emphasizes the importance of maintaining one's own cultural identity while also being open to other cultures.",
            "incorrect_answers": [
                "The proverb suggests that language is the most important factor in communication.",
                " The proverb suggests that learning multiple languages is easy and should be a priority.",
                " The proverb emphasizes the importance of being fluent in multiple languages for personal success."
            ]
        },
        {
            "difficulty": "2",
            "question": "ས་སྟོང་བསུབ། 'ཕྱི་མ་དགཔ་་་་་་་་་་་་་་་་་་་་་།། ནང་མ་དགཔ་གཏམ་གྱིས་བཤལ།།'?",
            "correct_answer": "ཆུ་གིས་བཤལ",
            "incorrect_answers": [
                "ཆརཔ་གི་བཤལ",
                " རོང་ཆུ་གི་བཤལ",
                " ཁྲི་ཆུ་གི་བཤལ"
            ]
        },
        {
            "difficulty": "2",
            "question": "It was mentioned that water can clean the:",
            "correct_answer": "External Dirt",
            "incorrect_answers": [
                "Internal Dirt",
                " Both external and internal dirt",
                " None of the above. "
            ]
        },
        {
            "difficulty": "2",
            "question": " ནང་མ་དགཔ་གཏམ་གྱིས་བཤལ།། ” ཟེར་མི་འདི་ ཨིང་སྐད་ནང་ལས་འབད་བ་ཅིན་",
            "correct_answer": "Clean the internal dirt with words. ",
            "incorrect_answers": [
                "Whether the inside is clean or not is known by words. ",
                " Words cannot clean the internal dirt. ",
                " Once the inside is filled with words, it is clean. "
            ]
        },
        {
            "difficulty": "2",
            "question": "What does the translated proverb 'Clean the external dirt with water; Clean the internal dirt with words' suggest about the power of words?",
            "correct_answer": "Words have the power to heal the internal wounds. ",
            "incorrect_answers": [
                "Words are useless when it comes to internal purity. ",
                " Words can only make things worse.  ",
                "Words are only useful for communication.  "
            ]
        },
        {
            "difficulty": "2",
            "question": "“བློ་གཏད་པའི་མི་གིས་ཧིང་བརྐུ།།”  ཟེར་མི་འདི་ ཨིང་སྐད་ནང་ལས་འབད་བ་ཅིན་",
            "correct_answer": "Trusted people can easily steal someone’s secrets. ",
            "incorrect_answers": [
                "One should trust everyone with their secrets.  ",
                " People should be cautious before trusting others with their secrets. ",
                "None  "
            ]
        },
        {
            "difficulty": "2",
            "question": "ས་སྟོང་བསུབ། “ མང་མའི་སྦུག་ལས་གདམ།། ་་་་་་་་་་་་་་་་་་་་་་ལས་བསལ།། ”:",
            "correct_answer": "ཉུང་མའི་སྦུག",
            "incorrect_answers": [
                "ཡོད་པའི་སྦུག",
                "མེད་པའི་སྦུག",
                "ལང་པའི་སྦུག "
            ]
        },
        {
            "difficulty": "2",
            "question": "“མང་མའི་སྦུག་ལས་གདམ།།” ཟེར་མི་འདི་ ཨིང་སྐད་ནང་ལས་འབད་བ་ཅིན་",
            "correct_answer": "Chosen from amongst many. ",
            "incorrect_answers": [
                "Need to be stingy when you have more. ",
                "Avoid being choosy when you have many options. ",
                "Need to be extravagant when you have more."
            ]
        },
        {
            "difficulty": "2",
            "question": "According to the translated proverb “ Chosen from amongst many. Selected from amongst few “, which of the following is more valuable?",
            "correct_answer": "Quality",
            "incorrect_answers": [
                "Quantity",
                "Neither is more valuable ",
                "It depends on the situation"
            ]
        },
        {
            "difficulty": "2",
            "question": "“ ཉུང ” ཟེར་མི་འདི་ ཨིང་སྐད་ནང་ལས་འབད་བ་ཅིན་",
            "correct_answer": "Less",
            "incorrect_answers": [
                "More",
                "Big",
                "Small"
            ]
        },
        {
            "difficulty": "2",
            "question": "What does the translated proverb ”Even if learned, the child will need the parent’s good counsel ” imply?་",
            "correct_answer": "Children need their parents' advice even if they are learned",
            "incorrect_answers": [
                "Children do not need their parents' advice",
                "Parents do not have any influence on their children's decision-making",
                "Parents' advice is not useful for children's growth"
            ]
        },
        {
            "difficulty": "2",
            "question": "ས་སྟོང་བསུབ། 'ཕག་ཤ་ཟ་ཚད་་་་་་་་་་་་་་་་་་་་་་་་་།། ཕག་རིན་འཇལ་ཚད་གནག་ལོག་ལོ།།'",
            "correct_answer": "འཛུམ་སེག་སེ",
            "incorrect_answers": [
                "ག་འཛུམ་མ་ཤོང་",
                "ཉམས་བཏགས",
                "གཟུགས་མ་བདེ"
            ]
        },
        {
            "difficulty": "2",
            "question": "“ ཕག་རིན་འཇལ་ཚད་གནག་ལོག་ལོ།། “ ཟེར་མི་འདི་ ཨིང་སྐད་ནང་ལས་འབད་བ་ཅིན་",
            "correct_answer": "But gloomy, when it is time to pay the price. ",
            "incorrect_answers": [
                "While measuring land for sale, shows a gloomy face. ་",
                "But gloomy, when it is time to pay with land. ",
                "Let others borrow money with a gloomy face."
            ]
        },
        {
            "difficulty": "2",
            "question": "“What is the translated proverb “cheerful, when pork was eaten; But gloomy, when its time to pay the price “ about?",
            "correct_answer": "Being happy when you receive something, but unhappy when you have to pay for it. ",
            "incorrect_answers": [
                "Eating pork. ",
                "Being happy when you pay for something.  ",
                "None"
            ]
        },
        {
            "difficulty": "2",
            "question": "As per the proverb, what is the mood of the person when pork is eaten?",
            "correct_answer": "Cheerful ",
            "incorrect_answers": [
                "Gloomy",
                "Indifferent ",
                "Annoyed"
            ]
        },
        {
            "difficulty": "2",
            "question": "In which of the following situations would it be appropriate to wear the clothes of the dead?",
            "correct_answer": "Never ",
            "incorrect_answers": [
                "When they are the only available clothes. ",
                "When it is  a cultural tradition. ",
                "When it is a requirement for a religious ceremony."
            ]
        },
        
{
    "difficulty": "3",
    "question": "ས་སྟོང་བསུབ། “ བླ་མའི་ཁྱི་བརྡུངན།། ་་་་་་་་་་་་་་་་་་་་་་་་་་་་་་་་་། “. ",
    "correct_answer": "བླ་མའི་ཐུགས་ཁར་ཕོག",
    "incorrect_answers": [
        "རང་ལས་བསགས།",
        "རང་སོ་བཏབཔ།",
        "རང་ལུ་ལས་ངན་ཕོག"
    ]
},

{
    "difficulty": "3",
    "question": "“ བླ་མའི་ཁྱི་བརྡུངན།། བླ་མའི་ཐུགས་ཁར་ཕོག། ” ཟེར་མི་འདི་ ཨིང་སྐད་ནང་ལས་འབད་བ་ཅིན་ ",
    "correct_answer": "Cane the priest’s dog and earn his wrath. ",
    "incorrect_answers": [
        "Cane the priest and you will be bitten by his dog. ",
        "Cane the priest’s dog and earn his forgiveness.",
        "Can the priest and his dog take no action? "
    ]
},

{
    "difficulty": "3",
    "question": "What does the phrase “ earn his wrath “ mean in the proverb translation?",
    "correct_answer": "To make someone angry",
    "incorrect_answers": [
        "To impress someone",
        "To make someone happy",
        "To disappoint someone"
    ]
},

{
    "difficulty": "3",
    "question": "What message does the translated proverb “Cane the priest’s dog and earn his wrath” convey?",
    "correct_answer": "If you mistreat someone’s pet, you might make them angry. ",
    "incorrect_answers": [
        "If you scold a priest, he will become violent. ",
        "If you  beat a dog, the priest will take the dog’s side.",
        "If you harm someone’s pet, the priest will forgive you"
    ]
},

{
    "difficulty": "3",
    "question": "As per one of the proverbs, which of the following will prevent a child from learning? ",
    "correct_answer": "Excessive love and affection",
    "incorrect_answers": [
        "Too much studying",
        "Lack of interest in the subject",
        "All of the above"
    ]
},

{
    "difficulty": "3",
    "question": "ས་སྟོང་བསུབ། “ ་་་་་་་་་་་་་་་་་་་་་་་་་་རྣམ་ཅོག་སྤུ་སོག་སོ།། དབང་མ་ཞུ་བའི་མགུ་ཏོག་ལེབ་ཏག་ག།”",
    "correct_answer": "ཆོས་མ་གོ་བའི་",
    "incorrect_answers": [
        "ཧ་མ་གོ་བའི་",
        "ཁུངས་མེད་པའི་",
        "ཉན་ཁུངས་མེད་པའི་"
    ]
},

{
    "difficulty": "3",
    "question": "“ དབང་མ་ཞུ་བའི་མགུ་ཏོག ” ཟེར་མི་འདི་ ཨིང་སྐད་ནང་ལས་འབད་བ་ཅིན་",
    "correct_answer": "Head that has not received the sacred blessings. ",
    "incorrect_answers": [
        "Eyes that have not received the sacred blessings. ",
        "Head that has no knowledge in it.",
        "Eyes that have not seen anything. "
    ]
},

{
    "difficulty": "3",
    "question": "What does 'Bristly the ear' represent in the proverb?",
    "correct_answer": "A dull or uneducated ear",
    "incorrect_answers": [
        "A prickly or rough ear",
        "An infected ear",
        "A misshapen ear"
    ]
},

{
    "difficulty": "3",
    "question": "What does 'Flat the head'represent in the proverb?",
    "correct_answer": "A head that has not received education",
    "incorrect_answers": [
        "A head that has no thoughts or ideas",
        "A head that is physically flat",
        "A head that has not been blessed"
    ]
},

{
    "difficulty": "3",
    "question": "What is the main idea behind 'If it concerns one's own interest, one can chew even a stone'?",
    "correct_answer": "One should be willing to do anything, no matter how difficult, for their own benefit.",
    "incorrect_answers": [
        "One should always prioritize their own interests over others'.",
        "One should be willing to make sacrifices for their own benefit.",
        "One should only act in their own interest if it does not harm others."
    ]
},

{
    "difficulty": "3",
    "question": "“དོམ་རྒྱབ་ཐལཝ་ད་དཔའ་རྟགས་འབལ།། བླམ་སྐུ་རྒྱབ་ཐལཝ་ད་་་་་་་་་་་།། ”",
    "correct_answer": "བསང་གཏང་",
    "incorrect_answers": [
        "དངོས་གྲུབ་བཞུ",
        "བྱིན་རླམས་བཞུ",
        "རིམ་གྲོ་གཏང"
    ]
},
{
    "difficulty": "3",
    "question": "“དོམ་རྒྱབ་ཐལཝ་ད་དཔའ་རྟགས་འབལ།། བླམ་སྐུ་རྒྱབ་ཐལཝ་ད་བསང་གཏང་།།” ཟེར་མི་དཔྱེ་གཏམ་ནང་ སེམས་ཅན་ག་འདི་ལུ་དཔྱེ་བཞག་ནུག? སེམས་ཅན་འདི་གི་མིང་ ཨིང་སྐད་ལས་འབད་བ་ཅིན་?",
    "correct_answer": "Bear",
    "incorrect_answers": [
        "Dog",
        "Fox",
        "Wolf"
    ]
},

{
    "difficulty": "3",
    "question": "What is the difference between 'Brandish the sword after the bear is departed' and 'Burn the incense after the lama is departed'?",
    "correct_answer": "One is about being cautious and the other is about showing respect",
    "incorrect_answers": [
        "One is about taking action and the other is about waiting",
        "One is about danger and the other is about peace",
        "One is about animals and the other is about humans"
    ]
},

{
    "difficulty": "3",
    "question": "What does the translated proverb 'Brandish the sword after the bear is departed; Burn the incense after the lama is departed' teach us?",
    "correct_answer": "To act upon the situation ",
    "incorrect_answers": [
        "To be respectful towards others",
        "To be brave and face danger head-on",
        "To be opportunistic and take advantage of situations"
    ]
},

{
    "difficulty": "3",
    "question": "Which of the following best describes the relationship between bone and flesh according to the translated proverb “ If bone is there, the growth of flesh is natural ”?",
    "correct_answer": "Bone is necessary for the growth of flesh",
    "incorrect_answers": [
        "Bone and flesh have no relationship",
        "Flesh grows first, and then bone develops",
        "Flesh and bone grow simultaneously"
    ]
},

{
    "difficulty": "3",
    "question": "ས་སྟོང་བསུབ། “ ཆུ་མའི་་་་་་་་་་་་་་་་་་་་།། ཕྱི་མའི་སྐྱིན་མ་འབྱོར་ཚུགས།། ”",
    "correct_answer": "སྐྱིན་ཚབ་མ་འབྱོར་རུང་",
    "incorrect_answers": [
        "བྲོཝ་མ་ཤེས་རུང་",
        "ལྟོ་མ་ཞིམ་རུང་",
        "བྲོཝ་མ་དགའ་རུང་"
    ]
},

{
    "difficulty": "3",
    "question": "“ སྐྱིན་མ་འབྱོར་ཚུགས ” ཟེར་མི་འདི་ ཨིང་སྐད་ནང་ལས་འབད་བ་ཅིན་",
    "correct_answer": "Repayment possible.",
    "incorrect_answers": [
        "Repayment impossible. ",
        "Borrowed flour able to be repaid. ",
        "Borrowed rice not able to repay. "
    ]
},

{
    "difficulty": "3",
    "question": "“ ཆུ་མའི་སྐྱིན་ཚབ་མ་འབྱོར་རུང་།། ཕྱི་མའི་སྐྱིན་མ་འབྱོར་ཚུགས།།” ཟེར་མི་འདི་ ཨིང་སྐད་ནང་ལས་འབད་བ་ཅིན་",
    "correct_answer": "Borrowed rice may not be repaid; But borrowed flour can be repaid",
    "incorrect_answers": [
        "Borrowed flour may not be repaid; But the borrowed rice can be repaid. ",
        "Borrowed water may not be repaid now; But can be repaid in the future once. ",
        "Borrowed water may not be repaid; But can be repaid soon."
    ]
},

{
    "difficulty": "3",
    "question": "In which context can the 'Borrowed rice may not be repaid; But borrowed flour can be repaid' be applied?",
    "correct_answer": "When dealing with debts",
    "incorrect_answers": [
        "When borrowing from friends and family",
        "When sharing resources in a community",
        "When cooking with rice and flour"
    ]
},

{
    "difficulty": "3",
    "question": "What is the reason behind the difficulty of making a poor person's son work?",
    "correct_answer": "Laziness",
    "incorrect_answers": [
        "Lack of education and resources.",
        "Health issues.",
        "None"
    ]
},

{
    "difficulty": "3",
    "question": "ས་སྟོང་བསུབ།  “ ཤེས་ཚད་རོགས་ལུ་མ་སྟོན།། ་་་་་་་་་་་་་་་་་་་་་་་་་་་་་་་་་་་་་།། མཐོང་ཚད་རོགས་ལུ་མ་སྟོན།། དྲགཔ་རོགས་ཀྱི་འབད་འོང་།། “",
    "correct_answer": "མཁསཔ་རོགས་ཀྱི་འབད་འོང",
    "incorrect_answers": [
        "མཁསཔ་རང་ར་འབད་དགོ",
        "མཁསཔ་རོགས་འགྱོ་འོང",
        "རང་བ་མཁསཔ་འབད་འོང"
    ]
},

{
    "difficulty": "3",
    "question": "“ ཤེས་ཚད་རོགས་ལུ་མ་སྟོན།། ” ཟེར་མི་འདི་ ཨིང་སྐད་ནང་ལས་འབད་བ་ཅིན་",
    "correct_answer": "Do not teach everything that one knows. ",
    "incorrect_answers": [
        "Knowledge is power and it should be kept secret.",
        "One should always trust others while sharing their knowledge. ",
        "Teach everything one knows."
    ]
},
{
    "difficulty": "3",
    "question": "'ཤེས་ཚད་རོགས་ལུ་མ་སྟོན།། མཁསཔ་རོགས་ཀྱི་འབད་འོང་།། མཐོང་ཚད་རོགས་ལུ་མ་སྟོན།། དྲགཔ་རོགས་ཀྱི་འབད་འོང་།།' ཟེར་མིའི་གོ་བ་འདི་ ཨིང་སྐད་ལས་འབད་བ་ཅིན་",
    "correct_answer": "One should be selective in sharing knowledge and discoveries",
    "incorrect_answers": [
        "Knowledge is power and should be kept secret",
        "Sharing knowledge and discoveries helps everyone",
        "One should never trust others with their secrets"
    ]
},

{
    "difficulty": "3",
    "question": "In which context can the 'Do not teach everything that one knows; Others might become learned; Do not show everything that one discovers; Others might own it' be applied?",
    "correct_answer": "In business and entrepreneurship",
    "incorrect_answers": [
        "In academia and research",
        "In personal relationships",
        "In cultural traditions and practices"
    ]
},

{
    "difficulty": "3",
    "question": "Which of the following best describes the message of the proverb 'Difficult for the cat to digest butter'?",
    "correct_answer": "It is important to know your limits.",
    "incorrect_answers": [
        "To be successful, you must take risks.",
        "Some things are impossible to achieve.",
        "Success requires hard work and effort."
    ]
},

{
    "difficulty": "3",
    "question": "ས་སྟོང་བསུབ། “ འཆམ་ཚེ་་་་་་་་་་་་་་་་་་་་་་་་་་་་་་།། རྒྱགས་ཚེ་ཁ་ལན་མི་འབྱོར།། “",
    "correct_answer": "སྙིང་གཏམ་མ་བཤད",
    "incorrect_answers": [
        "ཧིང་གཏམ་མ་བཤད",
        "ཧིང་གཏམ་མ་ཤེས",
        "སྙིང་གཏམ་མ་ཤེས"
    ]
},

{
    "difficulty": "3",
    "question": "“ འཆམ་ཚེ་སྙིང་གཏམ་མ་བཤད།། རྒྱགས་ཚེ་ཁ་ལན་མི་འབྱོར།། ” ཟེར་མིའི་གོ་བ་འདི་ ཨིང་སྐད་ལས་འབད་བ་ཅིན་",
    "correct_answer": "It is important to be cautious about sharing secrets during different phases of a relationship. ",
    "incorrect_answers": [
        "It is important to keep secrets from friends and family",
        "It is difficult to trust friends during times of quarrel",
        "Friends should not be trusted during arguments"
    ]
},

{
    "difficulty": "3",
    "question": "“ འཆམ་ཚེ་སྙིང་གཏམ་མ་བཤད།། ” ཟེར་མི་འདི་ ཨིང་སྐད་ནང་ལས་འབད་བ་ཅིན་",
    "correct_answer": "Do not tell secret in times of friendship",
    "incorrect_answers": [
        "Do not talk in times of friendship",
        "It is difficult to win an argument during times of quarrel",
        "It is difficult to defeat during the times of war"
    ]
},

{
    "difficulty": "3",
    "question": "“ རྒྱགས་ཚེ་ཁ་ལན་མི་འབྱོར།། ” ཟེར་མི་འདི་ ཨིང་སྐད་ནང་ལས་འབད་བ་ཅིན་",
    "correct_answer": "It is difficult to win an argument during times of quarrel",
    "incorrect_answers": [
        "Do not tell secret in times of friendship",
        "Do not talk in times of friendship",
        "It is difficult to defeat during the times of war"
    ]
},

{
    "difficulty": "3",
    "question": "Which of the following is the best example of the translated proverb “ Cross one mountain pass; And there is still the dark canopy of a valley to cross “?",
    "correct_answer": "A worker getting a promotion, but then facing more challenging tasks",
    "incorrect_answers": [
        "A person successfully completing a marathon, but then facing a difficult recovery process",
        "A student studying hard for an exam, but then finding out the exam has been postponed",
        "A traveler arriving at their destination, bu then realizing they forgot their passport"
    ]
},

{
    "difficulty": "3",
    "question": "ས་སྟོང་བསུབ།  '་་་་་་་་་་་་་་་་་་་་་།། ནོར་རང་དང་ཆ།།'",
    "correct_answer": "བུ་རོགས་དང་ཆ",
    "incorrect_answers": [
        "ཨ་ལུ་རོགས་དང་ཆ",
        "བུ་ཚུ་རོགས་དང་ཆ",
        "བུ་བུམོ་རོགས་དང་ཆ"
    ]
},

{
    "difficulty": "3",
    "question": "ནོར་རང་དང་ཆ།། ཟེར་མི་འདི་ ཨིང་སྐད་ནང་ལས་འབད་བ་ཅིན་:",
    "correct_answer": "Cattle be with oneself",
    "incorrect_answers": [
        "Cattle be sold",
        "Cattle be left to roam free",
        "Cattle be with others"
    ]
},

{
    "difficulty": "3",
    "question": "Which of the following is the most likely reason for the translated proverb “ Let children be with others and cattle be with oneself”?",
    "correct_answer": "To emphasize the importance of socialization for children",
    "incorrect_answers": [
        "To encourage farmers to keep cattle",
        "To discourage people from socializing",
        "To discourage people from keeping cattle"
    ]
},

{
    "difficulty": "3",
    "question": "བུ་རོགས་དང་ཆ།། ནོར་རང་དང་ཆ།། ཟེར་མི་འདི་ ཨིང་སྐད་ནང་ལས་འབད་བ་ཅིན་",
    "correct_answer": "Children should be allowed to socialize with others while cattle should be kept to oneself",
    "incorrect_answers": [
        "Children should be kept away from others",
        "Cattle should be kept away from others",
        "Children should be kept to oneself while cattle should be allowed to socialize with others"
    ]
},

{
    "difficulty": "3",
    "question": "Which of the following best describes the attitude implied by the translated proverb “ Clean up the drains before water arrives; Carry out the rituals before disease arrives ”?",
    "correct_answer": "Be proactive and take action before a problem occurs",
    "incorrect_answers": [
        "Don’t worry about it until it becomes a problem",
        "Let someone else deal with the problem",
        "It’s too late to do anything once the problem has started"
    ]
},

{
    "difficulty": "3",
    "question": "ས་སྟོང་བསུབ། 'མེ་ཆུང་ལས་བསད།། ་་་་་་་་་་་་་་་་་་་་་་་་་་་་་།།'",
    "correct_answer": "དགྲ་ཆུང་ལས་བཏུལ",
    "incorrect_answers": [
        "དགྲ་ཐབས་ཀྱི་བཏུལ",
        "རྩ་ཆུང་ལས་བཏོག",
        "ཤིང་ཆུང་ལས་བཏོག"
    ]
},

{
    "difficulty": "3",
    "question": "What’s the meaning of the translated proverb “ Douse the fire when it is small; Tame the enemy while still young ”?",
    "correct_answer": "It is important to act quickly to address problems before they get worse",
    "incorrect_answers": [
        "Fires are more dangerous than enemies",
        "Enemies cannot be tamed once they are old",
        "It is better to let problems solve themselves"
    ]
},

{
    "difficulty": "3",
    "question": "  མེ་ཆུང་ལས་བསད།། ཟེར་མི་འདི་ ཨིང་སྐད་ནང་ལས་འབད་བ་ཅིན་",
    "correct_answer": "Douse the fire when it is small",
    "incorrect_answers": [
        "Tame the enemy while still young",
        "Douse the enemy when still young",
        "Tame the enemy when fire is till small"
    ]
},

{
    "difficulty": "3",
    "question": "How might the translated proverb “ Douse the fire when it is small; Tame the enemy while still young  ” apply to personal relationships?",
    "correct_answer": "It is important to address conflicts early, before they become more difficult to resolve",
    "incorrect_answers": [
        "It is better to wait for conflicts to resolve themselves ",
        "Conflicts are not important in personal relationships",
        "It is important to resolve conflicts in personal relationships"
    ]
},

{
    "difficulty": "3",
    "question": "What is the significance of using water to clean external dirt in the proverb?",
    "correct_answer": "Water is symbolic of purity",
    "incorrect_answers": [
        "Water is easily accessible",
        "Water is a powerful cleaning agent",
        "Water is the only way to clean external dirt"
    ]
},


{
    "difficulty": "3",
    "question": "ས་སྟོང་བསུབ། “ ཆང་མར་འཛུལ།། ་་་་་་་་་་་་་་་་་་་་་་་།། ”",
    "correct_answer": "བློ་ཡར་འཐོན",
    "incorrect_answers": [
        "བྲོཝ་ཡར་འཐོན",
        "མགུ་ཏོ་ར་བཟི",
        "འཐབ་ཚིག་ཡར་འཐོན"
    ]
},

{
    "difficulty": "3",
    "question": "ཆང་མར་འཛུལ།། བློ་ཡར་འཐོན།། ཟེར་མིའི་གོ་བ་འདི་ ཨིང་སྐད་ལས་འབད་བ་ཅིན་",
    "correct_answer": "Drinking alcohol can cause a person to become more talkative",
    "incorrect_answers": [
        "Drinking alcohol leads to silence",
        "Drinking alcohol can cause a person to become more reserved",
        "Drinking alcohol leads to talking"
    ]
},


{
    "difficulty": "3",
    "question": " ‘ཆང་མར་འཛུལ།།’  ཟེར་མི་འདི་ ཨིང་སྐད་ནང་ལས་འབད་བ་ཅིན་ ",
    "correct_answer": "Down goes alcohol",
    "incorrect_answers": [
        "Alcohol drips down bottle",
        "IDown goes alcohol towards river",
        "Alcohol drips down the machine"
    ]
},

{
    "difficulty": "3",
    "question": "How does alcohol affect a person's behavior? ",
    "correct_answer": "It makes them more outgoing and talkative",
    "incorrect_answers": [
        "It makes them more quiet and reserved",
        "It makes them more argumentative",
        "It has no effect on their behavior"
    ]
},



{
    "difficulty": "3",
    "question": "Why do children need their parents' good counsel even if they are learned? ",
    "correct_answer": "All the mentioned options",
    "incorrect_answers": [
        "Because parents have more life experience and wisdom",
        "Because children lack the emotional maturity to make sound decisions",
        "Because parents have a better understanding of the child's personality and capabilities"
    ]
},




{
    "difficulty": "3",
    "question": "ས་སྟོང་བསུབ། ‘བུ་ལང་ཤོར་བཏང་པ་གཅེས་ཕྲུག་མེན།། རྒྱུ་ཆུད་ཟད་བཏང་པ་་་་་་་་་་་་་་་་་་་་་།།’  ",
    "correct_answer": "སྦྱིན་པ་མེན",
    "incorrect_answers": [
        "བྱིན་པ་ཡིན",
        "ལེགས་ཤོམ་ཡིན",
        "བླུན་པོ་ཡིན"
    ]
},


{
    "difficulty": "3",
    "question": " ‘བུ་ལང་ཤོར་བཏང་པ་གཅེས་ཕྲུག་མེན།།’   ཟེར་མི་འདི་ ཨིང་སྐད་ནང་ལས་འབད་བ་ཅིན་",
    "correct_answer": "Encouraging reckless habits in the child is not affection",
    "incorrect_answers": [
        "Giving too much affection to a child can lead to reckless behavior",
        "Being reckless with one’s wealth is form of charity.",
        "Wasting money on charity is not helpful"
    ]
},



{
    "difficulty": "3",
    "question": "How does the proverb ‘Encouraging reckless habits in the child is not affection; Squandering wealth without prudence is not charity’ apply to parenting?",
    "correct_answer": "Parents should teach their children to be responsible and careful with their actions.",
    "incorrect_answers": [
        "Parents should let their children do whatever they want.",
        "Parents should be reckless with their children's upbringing.",
        "Parents should spend money on their children without thinking about the consequences."
    ]
},



{
    "difficulty": "3",
    "question": "According to the proverb, what is not charity?",
    "correct_answer": "Spending money recklessly",
    "incorrect_answers": [
        "Donating money to the poor",
        "Investing in a business",
        "Saving money for future generations"
    ]
},




{
    "difficulty": "3",
    "question": "What lesson can be learned from the translated proverb “ cheerful, when pork was eaten; But gloomy, when its time to pay the price ”?",
    "correct_answer": "Be prepared to pay the price for what you receive",
    "incorrect_answers": [
        "Don't eat pork",
        "Always be happy when receiving something",
        "None"
    ]
}



    ]
}